Alright then friends, let's move ahead and talk about yet another concept which is at the core
of programming languages not just Java and that is how you handle exceptions. In short,
we call this as exception handling.
Again, I'm just using my right board first, but the digital wide board to make it more
understandable more clear for you before we dive in and write some actual code because
you'll be seeing all along the scores how this is different as this is completely hands-on
and we take it from absolute scratch as promised. So, exception handling, before we talk about
exception handling, let's talk about exceptions, what are exceptions, right? What is obviously the
English term exception and does anything or any examples come to your mind, any exceptions that
happen in your everyday life or has happened until now, think about it, or is the video come back
and then map to what I say. So, exceptions in the real world can be anything that is not usual,
not something that you expect every day to have. Like say for example, go forward
you're traveling and there is an accident while you're traveling while you're driving your bike.
That is an exception because every day let's say for six months going to your college or going
to your university or going to your workplace that didn't happen, you started from whom
reached your workplace or your university in a safe manner and that was fine, but on one fine day
an accident happened and things took a bad turn. Another case of exception would be an earthquake,
right? It doesn't happen every day, but once it does, can wreck havoc. Another one would be floods,
right? Because floods don't come every other day, but when they do, they can just ruin everything
that we earn until now. And yet another exception that comes to mind is a theft at your hope,
go forward, right? Because again, it doesn't happen every day, but can happen any time, any day.
Those are all exceptions now use and once you understand them, now then that is how do we handle them?
In terms of earthquake, how do you handle exceptions? Obviously you cannot get rid of them completely,
not yet, but you prepare for it. You create earthquake proof houses and in terms of floods,
how do you prepare? How do you handle that kind of an exception? You know that who are the people
who are more prone, who are more susceptible, who are more vulnerable to flooding are the ones who
lie, who stay, or who live in low-lying areas, right? The ones who don't, they're less susceptible.
And then how you prepare is you put all your gold, cash and precious belongings on the second floor,
not on the, not in the basement, not on the down floor, right? That's how you prepare because
even if the flood has come in, obviously your data on the second floor would be saved in all
probability. Then in terms of theft, right? The, the fear of theft is how you prepare is you get a good
lock. That's the first step that you take. The second step is that you only put that in a particular
room, not in all rooms. The third one is you hire a security guard from a security agency and put them
outside your room where you'll be longing start at all times, right? So those are the steps,
the measures that you take. In terms of programming again, there are exceptions, situations like,
for example, if you try to divide something by zero, that is something which hasn't been defined yet,
right? And Java obviously would not be stuck, that's an exception, that is arithmetic exception,
we call that, right? And how do you handle it is what we are, we are going to discuss,
what is that security guard that you're going to put in here, right? And for all those
exceptions, not used like, as I said, divided by zero or there is a file that was on your system,
but a virus came in and deleted that the same code that existed and worked before doesn't work
now out of out of nowhere. Let's again, in exceptions, not you. How do you handle that is what we're
going to talk about that spying not found, but all these exceptions in our use for Java to not be
stuck and not be embarrassed, they created different exception classes for us in the API,
and they threw exceptions, we say, an exception is thrown that we need to handle, right? And how
do you handle it? You put that vulnerable piece of code in something called a tri-catch.
Right, put your vulnerable code right here, that can be one line, 10 line or 50 lines,
put place that in the tri-block, and after the catch, put in the appropriate exception handle,
and an object of that, I'll just call it ref, and then do something with that here,
with that exception, right? So what happens is in the tri-block, you put in your vulnerable code
that is susceptible to dangers that you know, right? And then afterwards, you put in the catch,
if the exception was thrown, because the exceptions are never guaranteed to be thrown, right? You
can only assume you can only think of them that they're possible because earthquakes never
happen every day, floods don't come every day, tifts don't happen every day, right? They can
happen once in a while. So I, you as a developer, would never know whether an exception would be
thrown or not. Is it guaranteed to be thrown or not? When it would be thrown, but you always know
as a developer, you would always know that in my code, there is a vulnerable piece of code,
which is susceptible to this kind of danger, because at my home, I know if I have some golden
cash, I am vulnerable to tifts, right? If I don't have any golden cash, so I'm not, I can sleep
peacefully, right? So you would always know, that's why I'll just reiterate that. So that is,
as a developer, you would never know for sure whether an exception would be thrown or not,
when it would be thrown or not, at what time, but you would always know, if I have a vulnerable
deed in my code, and that's when I say, please take care, and how do you take care, that is
right, thank you, put that vulnerable code here, see, if the exception doesn't come, your code
runs fine, cash block is skipped, and the control resumes here, but if somewhere in the try, the
exception is raised, the exception is thrown, the other code in the try would not be executed,
immediately comes out and looks for its appropriate latch handler, and you take that with that
variable, and then do something with that here, right, as does or as or that security card
do with the theme that he would catch, right? So that is how this thing works, let's go ahead
and write some actual code to demonstrate try cash for you, and how exception handling works in job.